Michel Licht Papers
Michel Licht Papers
1910-1957
Licht, Michel, 1893-1953.
1.25 linear ft.
Papers of the Russian-born Yiddish poet and translator. Collection includes correspondence; manuscript poems and translations in English, Russian, and Yiddish; notes; and 9 wood-mounted metal cuts from designs by wife Evelyn Licht which were used in various of her husband's publications. Notable correspondents include James Branch Cabell, T.S. Eliot, Albert Einstein, Donald Gallup, Clement Greenberg, George Platt Lynes, Marianne Morre, Norman Holmes Pearson, Ezra Pound, John Crowe Ransom, Karl Jay Shapiro, Gertrude Stein, Wallace Stevens and William Carlos Williams.
149134
Biographical History
Michel Licht (1893-1953) was a Russian-born Yiddish poet and translator. Following his emigration to the United States in 1913, Licht's poems and Russian and Yiddish translations in English appeared in various American periodicals, including The New York Call and Pagan.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning 1910 to 1957, the Michel Licht Papers comprises correspondence, writings, and memorabilia.
Reflecting Licht's interest in the American avant-garde literary movement of the 1920s, the Correspondence includes letters of James Cabell Branch, T. S. Eliot, Marianne Moore, Ezra Pound, Gertrude Stein, Wallace Stevens, and William Carlos Williams. Other literary and publishing industry correspondents include Clement Greenberg, Guy Holt, George Platt Lynes, Norman Holmes Pearson, John Crowe Ransom, and Karl Jay Shapiro. A selected index to correspondence follows the box list. There is also a selection of unidentified letters and postcards of foreign origin.
Writings include Licht's published books in Yiddish and holograph and typescript manuscripts in English, Russian, and Yiddish. In addition to several of Licht's English and Russian poems, there are also a number of his English translations of French, Russian, and Yiddish poetry by various authors.
Memorabilia includes printed material and nine wood-mounted metal cuts from designs by wife Evelyn Licht which were used in various of her husband's publications.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is divided into English and other languages, and within that arranged chronologically. Writings and Memorabilia are arranged alphabetically by type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Literature -- American Fiction; Literature -- American Poetry; Cabell, James Branch, 1879-1958.; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955.; Eliot, T. S. (Thomas Stearns), 1888-1965.; Gallup, Donald Clifford, 1913-2000.; Greenberg, Clement, 1909-1994.; Licht, Michel, 1893-1953.; Lynes, George Platt, 1907-1955.; Moore, Marianne, 1887-1972.; Pearson, Norman Holmes, 1909-1975.; Pound, Ezra, 1885-1972.; Ransom, John Crowe, 1888-1974.; Shapiro, Karl Jay, 1913-2000.; Stein, Gertrude, 1874-1946.; Stevens, Wallace, 1879-1955.; Williams, William Carlos, 1883-1963.; American poetry -- Translations into Yiddish.; Modernism (Literature) -- Translations.; Poetry, Modern -- 20th century -- Tranlations.; Poetry, Translating.; Poets, Yiddish -- United States.; Translators -- United States.; Yiddish poetry -- Translations into English.; Correspondence.; Poems.; Translations.; Poets.; Translators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Evelyn Licht, 1962.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - English, 1918-1957; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Other, 1910-1938 (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Gezamlte Lider, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Letste Lider, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Moderne Amerikaner Poezye, 1954 (Box 1)
    - Nit tsu Dertseyin, 1955 (Box 1)
    - Oyf di Randn, 1956 (Box 1)
    - Velvi Goth, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Chronology of Licht's poetry and prose, book contents (Box 2)
  - Notebook contents (Box 2)
  - Notes (English) on authors, books, music, etc., 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Poetry
    - English poems (Box 2)
    - Russian poems (Box 2)
    - Translations by Licht of Chinese pictographs in Yiddish (Box 2)
    - Translations by Licht of the French poems of Sully Prudhomme (Box 2)
    - Translations by Licht of Russian poems (Box 2)
    - Translations by Licht of his Yiddish poems (Box 2)
    - Translations by Licht of Yiddish poems by various authors (Box 2)
  - Miscellany
    - Untitled biography of French dancer Yvette Chavire (English), typescript ms. (Box 2)
    - Russian (Box 2)
    - Yiddish, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Memorabilia
  - Printed material (Box 2)
  - Wood-mounted metal cuts used in Licht's publications (from designs of Evelyn Licht), 3 of 9 (Box 2)
  - Wood-mounted metal cuts used in Licht's publications (from designs of Evelyn Licht), 6 of 9 (Box 3)
Selected index to correspondence
Cabell, James Branch 1927 Mar. 15? (outgoing) 1927 Mar. 21
Commentary 1953 Aug. 28
Einstein, Albert see Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists, Inc.
Eliot, Thomas Stearns 1926 Feb. 12 (outgoing) 1927 Mar. 11
Emergency Committee of Atomic Scientists, Inc. 1947 Mar. 20 1947 Apr. 8
Faber and Faber ltd. 1956 Oct. 9 1956 Oct. 24
Gallup, Donald 1954 Feb. 3 1954 Oct. 4 1957 Jan. 3
Greenberg, Clement 1953 Aug. 28
Holt, Guy see Robert M. McBride & Company
Kaylor, V. B. see Alfred A. Knopf, Inc.
The Kenyon Review 1953 Oct. 12
Alfred A. Knopf, Inc. 1927 Jan. 4 (outgoing) 1927 Jan. 18 1927 Jan. 20 (outgoing) 1927 Jan. 22
Lynes, George Platt 1927 Feb. 2 1927 Feb. 7 (outgoing) 1927 Mar. 18 1927 Mar. 23 (outgoing)
Robert M. McBride & Company 1925 Nov. 10 (outgoing) 1925 Nov. 21 1925 Dec. 24 1926 Jan. 3 (outgoing) 1926 Jan. 28 1926 Feb. 22 (outgoing) 1926 Oct. 25
Moore, Marianne 1942 Mar. 22 1941 Jan. 28 (outgoing) 1942 Apr. (copy of fragment)
New Republic 1954 May 10
Pearson, Norman Holmes 1941 Dec. 24
Poetry 1954 Feb. 7
Pound, Ezra 1918 Dec. 20?
Ransom, John Crowe 1953 Oct. 12
Shapiro, Karl Jay 1954 Feb. 7
Stein, Gertrude 1927 Feb. 4 (outgoing) 1927 Mar. 1
Stevens, Wallace 1954 Oct. 14
Williams, William Carlos 1932 July 12